MERGEN NAIDOO

CONTACT



Johannesburg, South Africa

Dar Es Salaam, Tanzania

CERTIFICATIONS

AZURE AI FUNDAMENTALS

Microsoft 2020

AZURE FUNDAMENTALS

Microsoft 2020

AWS CLOUD PRACTITIONER

Amazon 2019

ASSOCIATE PROFESSIONAL RISK MANAGER

Professional Risk Managers' International Association 2011

EDUCATION

B.COM (INFORMATICS) HONOURS

University of South Africa 2005 - 2007

B.COM (INFORMATION SYSTEMS)

University of Kwazulu Natal 2000 - 2002

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Experienced Data Head specializing in Analytics, Data Engineering, Machine Learning, Data Science, Data Management, and Data Strategy.

17 Years of experience in Financial Services (Banking and Insurance).

Has built many teams with skills in Data Engineering, ML Engineering, Data Science, Business Intelligence, Product support in both SA and London.

Regularly interacts with Business and IT stakeholders at the Executive,

Management and staff levels to help guide Data Strategy and Digital transformation objectives.

WORK EXPERIENCE

DATA AND AI HEAD- CIB TECHNOLOGY (DIGITAL)

STANDARD BANK | APR 2019 - June 2021

- Led a team of Data engineers, ML engineers and Data Analysts
- Formulate the CIB Data Strategy and ensure alignment with the business strategy and KPI's
- Successful Implementations of several Data Science and Business Intelligence solutions
- Influencing and driving collaboration across cross functional teams to deliver client value solutions
- Consult with BU leadership to develop an understanding of the current and future business needs supported by systems and how these can be better enabled through data
- Develop strategic, tactical and operational plans to meet the data needs of the business line and ensure that IT capabilities are responsive to the needs of the business line's growth and operational objectives
- Collaborate with Enterprise Architecture to create Information, Data architecture standards and simplify the current data environment
- Provide thought leadership and build partnerships with business and data enablers within business
- Help build the modern data capabilities e.g. machine learning, analytics and data engineering

SENIOR MANAGER- CIB DATA SCIENCE

STANDARD BANK | APR 2016 - MAR 2019

- Founded the CIB Data Science Practice
- Led a team of Data Scientists and Data Engineers
- Built federated capability across CIB
- Training curriculum created and executed for Data Scientists; Data Engineers; Executives; Data Science boot camps and Graduates
- CIB Data Science Graduate programme creation and execution
- Implemented several Data Science use cases on Prem and on Cloud
- Participation in Group wide guilds to help drive knowledge sharing and collaboration across the group

SKILLS

Data Strategy

Data Analytics

Data Governance

Data Science

Data Engineering

Technology Strategy

Project and Portfolio Management

Managerial Finance

Business Analysis

SDLC

AWARDS

MARK OF EXCELLENCE WINNER

Standard Bank 2016

WORK EXPERIENCE CONTINUED

SENIOR MANAGER- CIB DATA PROGRAMME

STANDARD BANK | MAR 2015 - MAR 2016

- Drive data consistency across Risk, Finance, Treasury & Capital Management
- Rationalisation of data feeds
- Defined data integration strategy for Risk& Finance IT
- Execution of Risk and Finance data integration projects
- Drive CIB Data Governance
- Oversight of several CIB Compliance IT related projects

REGIONAL HEAD- MARKET RISK IT (AFRICA)

STANDARD BANK | JUN 2013 - FEB 2015

- Technology Strategy development
- Managed a team of programme managers, project managers, software developers, business analyst and testers
- Delivery oversight of multiple projects
- Conducted monthly steering committees with Business Execs
- Management of the Market Risk IT global operations portfolio (South Africa, Rest of Africa and International)
- Stakeholder management: Market Risk, Front Office, Finance, Regulatory Reporting and Product Control
- Alignment to King III, ITIL and COBIT industry practices

OPERATIONS MANAGER- MARKET RISK IT

STANDARD BANK | JAN 2010 - JUN 2013

- Managed Global Market Risk IT operations which included incident management, change management, release management, IT risk and security management
- Managed and developed a team of business analysts, software developers, and production support analysts in Johannesburg and London Head-offices
- Managed inter-group IT service level agreements and relationships
- Business continuity and disaster recovery planning
- Infrastructure management
- Solution Architecture

SENIOR BUSINESS ANALYST- MARKET RISK IT

STANDARD BANK | SEP 2007 - DEC 2009

- Analysis and design of a Market Risk reporting solution for Africa
- Business process mapping
- Strategic alignment of International and Africa data models
- User interface design
- User acceptance testing
- Development of training material

STRENGHTS

Formulating fit for purpose strategy

Strong communication skills

Effective at building strong relationships

Influencing and driving collaboration

WORK EXPERIENCE CONTINUED

BUSINESS ANALYST

DISCOVERY LIFE | NOV 2005 - AUG 2007

- Researching, defining and documenting business requirements for New Business, Servicing and Underwriting systems
- User experience design
- Production support
- Managed and conducted user acceptance testing
- Monitored competitor and industry activities
- Development of Training Material

PRODUCT ANALYST

STANDARD BANK | SEP 2003 - OCT 2005

- Product Analysis
 - Project development for International Banking, FX trading and International Trade systems
 - o Design specifications
 - Project management
 - User Acceptance Testing
 - Research
- Product Support
 - o Incident management
 - SLA Management

ANALYST

ACCENTURE | FEB 2003 - JUL 2003

- Based at the Johannesburg Stock Exchange
- Activity Based Costing Modelling
- Evaluation of time recording tools for project costing
- Capital Markets Research
- Development of training material

REFERENCES

AVAILABLE ON REQUEST

LINKEDIN PROFILE

https://www.linkedin.com/in/mergen-naidoo-4b49a638/